<metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>James A. Falcone</origin><pubdate>2018</pubdate><title>Changes in anthropogenic influences on streams and rivers in the conterminous U.S. over the last 40 years, derived for 16 data themes</title><geoform>Comma-separated text files</geoform><onlink>https://doi.org/10.5066/F7XW4J1J</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This product consists of time-series calculations of anthropogenic characteristics derived for 16 data themes for multiple scales covering the conterminous United States.  The characteristics are those which (a) have consistent data sources, and (b) have the potential to affect the water quality of streams and rivers.   All 16 data themes are provided for Hydrologic Unit Code level-10 (HUC-10) boundaries (n = 15,458).  Additionally, measures of land use and imperviousness are provided for U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (USEPA) Level 4 ecoregions (n = 967) and for U.S. counties (n = 3,109). The data may be scaled up to broader areas; that is, HUC-10 data may be scaled up to HUC-8, 6, 4, or HUC-2 areas,  Level 4 ecoregions may be scaled up to Levels 3, 2, and 1, and counties may be scaled up to States or multi-state regions.  The 16 broad categories of data are: (1) atmospheric  deposition (1985-2012), (2) agricultural production and livestock (1969-2012), (3) land in the Conservation Reserve Program (1986-2014), (4) dams and reservoirs (1972-2013), (5) housing unit density (1970-2010) and population density (1990-2010), (6) imperviousness (1974-2012 and 2001-2011), (7) irrigation (1969-2012 and 2002-2012), (8) land use (1974-2012 and 2001-2011), (9) land use in 200-meter flow distance riparian buffers (1974-2012), (10) nitrogen and phosphorus application from fertilizer (1987-2012), (11) nitrogen and phosphorus application from manure (1982-2012),  (12) pesticide application (1992-2012), (13) road salt application (1992-2012), (14) timber and forest cutting (1999-2012), (15) freshwater withdrawal water use (1985-2010), and (16) wastewater treatment plant nitrogen and phosphorus yields (1978-2012). The temporal resolution of the source data vary by dataset, and range from annual to decadal data. The data posted here consist of tabular data and shapefiles to which the data may be joined.</abstract><purpose>These data are intended to provide a framework in which watershed-specific studies of water quality in streams and rivers may be analyzed. The focus of the data is on anthropogenic changes over time.</purpose><supplinf>Each of the datasets provided here contains data for a particular theme, for example Atmospheric Deposition or Pesticide Use.  The tables provided in each dataset are in comma-separated text format. Each dataset has a companion metadata .xml file which describes the data, methods, and references for those data.  A supplemental overview table in Microsoft Excel format (summary_processing_scales.xlsx) is provided showing the scale(s) of calculations for each data theme.
For every data theme, calculations are given for HUC-10 boundaries. These were obtained on January 9, 2018 from the U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA) National Resources Conservation Service (NRCS) at https://nrcs.app.box.com/v/huc/folder/39640323180 (National Resources Conservation Service, 2018). Each table contains 15,458 rows, one for each HUC-10 area.  For some data layers, namely Imperviousness, Landuse, and Timber, calculations are also given for counties (n = 3,109; National Historic Geographic Information System, 2013), and U.S. Environmental Protection Agency Level IV ecoregions (n = 967) (U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, 2013).  The processing and setup for each of these boundary datasets is described below under Process Steps.
Only one dataset has missing data for some records, for which "NA" is provided in place of a numeric value; that is the Landuse_Riparian dataset (dataset #10). For 38 records in this dataset NHDPlus streamlines did not extend into the HUC-10, and thus no "riparian zones" existed (for more detail see metadata for that dataset).
The geospatial processing for the project was based on datasets which all used the following standard projection information: PROJECTION ALBERS, UNITS meters, SPHEROID GRS1980, DATUM NAD83, PARAMETERS, 29 30 0.000, 45 30 0.000, -96 00 0.000, 23 00 0.000, 0.0, 0.0.
This data release contains 19 zip files, one with tabular boundary identification information, one with shapefiles of the boundaries used, and 16 others with data for each of the themes.  Each data theme zip file contains one or more tables in comma-separated text format. The boundary shapefiles consist of shapefiles for the HUC-10s, counties, and Level 4 ecoregions to which the tabular data may be joined by their corresponding "uniqid" field. 
NOTE: Users should note the length of some variable names, and that in some GIS operations variable names may be truncated after joining; for example joining in ArcMap then resaving as a new shapefile typically truncates names to the first 10 characters. Most variable names here are intentionally fairly descriptive; that is, they indicate the year, the scale (e.g. HUC-10), the parameter being measured, in cases the type (e.g. NLCD vs NWALT), and sometimes the units.  It was felt it was preferable to keep descriptive variable names and allow users to change them themselves if the intention was to join them in an operation that might truncate them, as opposed to providing short but undescriptive variable names.
A separate .xml file is contained within each zip file, which includes source data references.  An overview of the data zip files is given here:
Boundary_IDs: Three tables giving the identification and area of the HUC-10s, counties, and Level 4 ecoregions used in data calculations.
Dataset 1: Atmos_Dep: Five tables with data for wet ion deposition for calcium (Ca), chloride (Cl), magnesium (Mg), nitrogen (N), and sulfate (SO4), annual data for the years 1985—2012.
Dataset 2: CoA_Production: Eleven tables with agricultural production data per unit area, compiled from USDA Census of Agriculture (CoA) data, for example bushels of soybeans per square kilometer (sq km), or cows per sq km. Data for soybeans, wheat, corn for grain, corn for silage, rice, cotton, alfalfa-hay, cows, hogs, chickens, and sheep. Data are for COA years (approximately every five years), from 1969-2012.
Dataset 3: CRP: One table with proportion of total cropland area in the USDA Conservation Reserve Program (CRP), annual data for the years 1986-2014.
Dataset 4: Dams-Reservoirs: One table with information about hydrologic modifications in the form of dams and reservoir presence and storage, for ten year periods from 1972-2013.
Dataset 5: Housing-Population: One table with mean housing density for 10 year periods from 1970-2010, and one table with mean population density from Census block data for 10-year periods from 1990-2010.
Dataset 6: Imperviousness: Two tables with percent imperviousness from the National Land Cover Dataset (NLCD) (every five years, 2001-2011) and from the NAWQA Wall-to-wall Anthropogenic Landuse Trends (NWALT) product (every 10 years, 1974-2012).
Dataset 7: Irrigation: Two tables with percent of land in irrigation from USDA Census of Agriculture county-level data (every five years, 1969-2012), and from more spatially detailed USGS data (every 5 years, 2002-2012).
Dataset 8: LandUse: Twenty-four tables with land use and land cover data from the NLCD (every five years, 2001-2011), and the NWALT (every 10 years, 1974-2012).
Dataset 9: LandUse_Riparian: Five tables with land use in riparian zones, from the NWALT (every 10 years, 1974-2012). Riparian zones are defined as areas of 200-meter flow distance to networked stream lines and water bodies.
Dataset 10: N-P_from_fert: Four tables with data for estimates of nitrogen and phosphorus from fertilizer application, annual data from 1987-2012.
Dataset 11: N-P_from_manure: Two tables with data for estimates of nitrogen and phosphorus from manure, five year periods from 1982-2012.
Dataset 12: Pesticide_Use: Seventeen tables with estimates of pesticide use, five year periods from 1992-2012.
Dataset 13: Road salt: One table with estimated road salt application, annually from 1992-2015.
Dataset 14: Timber: One table with percent of watershed with timber or forest cutting, annually from 1999-2012.
Dataset 15: Water_Use: One table with estimates of total freshwater withdrawals, from USGS water use data for five year periods from 1985-2010.
Dataset 16: WWTPs: One table with data regarding waste water treatment plants (WWTPs), 1978-2012, including nitrogen and phosphorus yields and density of WWTPs for approximate two year intervals from the USEPA Clean Water Needs Survey data.
References:
National Historical Geographic Information System, 2013, U.S. geographic summary data and boundary files, 2010: National Historical Geographic Information System, Integrated Public Use Microdata Series (IPUMS), county boundaries, accessed February 1, 2013 at: https://www.nhgis.org/.
National Resources Conservation Service, 2017, Watershed boundary dataset (WBD): National Resources Conservation Service, U.S. Department of Agriculture, available at https://www.nrcs.usda.gov/wps/portal/nrcs/main/national/technical/nra/geo/,  accessed January 9, 2018 from https://nrcs.app.box.com/v/huc/folder/39640323180. 
U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, 2013, Level IV ecoregions of the conterminous United States: U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Office of Research and Development – National Health and Environmental Effects Research Laboratory, accessed November 17, 2017 at: https://www.epa.gov/eco-research/level-iii-and-iv-ecoregions-continental-united-states.</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><rngdates><begdate>19690101</begdate><enddate>20141231</enddate></rngdates></timeinfo><current>observed</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>As needed</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-124.886</westbc><eastbc>-66.879</eastbc><northbc>49.384</northbc><southbc>24.381</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>None</themekt><themekey>Watershed</themekey><themekey>NHDPlus</themekey><themekey>inlandWaters</themekey><themekey>Geospatial Datasets</themekey><themekey>Geographic Information Systems</themekey><themekey>Imperviousness</themekey><themekey>Land use</themekey><themekey>Land use change</themekey><themekey>Atmospheric Deposition</themekey><themekey>Census of Agriculture</themekey><themekey>Conservation Practices</themekey><themekey>Crop Reserve Program</themekey><themekey>Trends</themekey><themekey>Hydrologic Modifications</themekey><themekey>Riparian Land Use</themekey><themekey>Nitrogen application</themekey><themekey>Phosphorus application</themekey><themekey>Fertilizer</themekey><themekey>Population change</themekey><themekey>Housing</themekey><themekey>Urbanization</themekey><themekey>Road Salt</themekey><themekey>Waste Water Treatment Plants</themekey><themekey>Water Use</themekey></theme><place><placekt>None</placekt><placekey>United States</placekey><placekey>Conterminous US</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None. Please see 'Distribution Info' for details.</accconst><useconst>Please read use constraints for individual data layers, as applicable.</useconst><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>US Geological Survey, National Water Quality project.</cntorg><cntper>James Falcone</cntper></cntorgp><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing</addrtype><address>12201 Sunrise Valley Dr.</address><address>MS 413 National Center</address><city>Reston</city><state>VA</state><postal>20192</postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>703-648-5008</cntvoice><cntemail>jfalcone@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac><datacred>Grateful acknowledgment to the following people: Nancy Baker for providing the pesticide data, Michael Wieczorek and Wes Stone for providing the conservation practices groupings and data, and Richard Moore for providing the flow-distance raster.  Great thanks to Nancy Baker for performing entire product review.</datacred><native>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft [Unknown] Version 6.2 (Build 9200) ; Esri ArcGIS 10.6 (Build 8321) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</native></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>See individual data layers, as applicable.</attraccr></attracc><logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted.</logic><complete>Data are complete</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>A formal accuracy assessment of the horizontal positional information in the data set has not been conducted.</horizpar></horizpa><vertacc><vertaccr>A formal accuracy assessment of the vertical positional information in the data set has either not been conducted, or is not applicable.</vertaccr></vertacc></posacc><lineage><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>National Resources Conservation Service</origin><pubdate>20180109</pubdate><title>Published Hydrologic Unit Code boundaries</title><geoform>Vector Digital Data Set (polygon)</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>online</pubplace><publish>National Resources Conservation Service</publish></pubinfo><onlink>https://nrcs.app.box.com/v/huc/folder/39640323180</onlink></citeinfo></srccite><typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20171002</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><srccurr>access date</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>National Resources Conservation Service, 2017</srccitea><srccontr>HUC-10 boundaries used in data calculations.</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>National Historical Geographic Information System (NHGIS)</origin><pubdate>20130201</pubdate><title>U.S. Geographic Summary Data and Boundary Files, published 2010 county boundaries</title><geoform>Vector Digital Data Set (polygon)</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>online</pubplace><publish>National Historical Geographic Information System</publish></pubinfo><onlink>https://www.nhgis.org/</onlink></citeinfo></srccite><typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20130201</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><srccurr>access date</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>National Historical Geographic Information System, 2013</srccitea><srccontr>County boundaries used in data calculations.</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (USEPA)</origin><pubdate>20130416</pubdate><title>Level III and IV ecoregions of the continental United States</title><geoform>Vector Digital Data Set (polygon)</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>online</pubplace><publish>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency</publish></pubinfo><onlink>https://www.epa.gov/eco-research/level-iii-and-iv-ecoregions-continental-united-states</onlink></citeinfo></srccite><typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20171117</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><srccurr>access date</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, 2013</srccitea><srccontr>Level IV ecoregion boundaries used in data calculations.</srccontr></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>(1) 2010 county boundaries in polygon format were downloaded from the National Historical Geographic Information System at https://www.nhgis.org/.  Boundaries were subset to the conterminous U.S.  A unique identifier for GIS processing was added and the area in square kilometers was calculated from the polygons. The polygons were then converted to a 100-meter grid.  There are 3,109 resultant county areas.</procdesc><procdate>20130209</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>(2) USEPA Level IV ecoregion boundaries in polygon format were downloaded from the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency at https://www.epa.gov/eco-research/level-iii-and-iv-ecoregions-continental-united-states. A unique identifier for GIS processing was added and the area in square kilometers was calculated from the polygons.  The polygons were then converted to a 100-meter grid.  There are 967 resultant level IV ecoregion areas.</procdesc><procdate>20171117</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>(3) HUC-10 boundaries in polygon format were downloaded from the National Resources Conservation Service at https://nrcs.app.box.com/v/huc/folder/39640323180.  Boundaries were subset to those covering the conterminous U.S. Because, unlike the county and ecoregion boundaries, some HUC-10 boundaries extend considerably into areas outside the land area of CONUS (for example into Canada, Mexico, and oceans), and the vast majority of data layers to be processed were limited to only the land area of CONUS, the HUC-10 boundaries were clipped against the level IV ecoregion boundaries above.  A number of "sliver" polygons which resulted from this were deleted. A unique identifier for GIS processing was added and the area in square kilometers was calculated from the polygons. The polygons were then converted to a 100-meter grid.  There are 15,458 resultant HUC-10 areas.</procdesc><procdate>20180109</procdate></procstep></lineage></dataqual><distinfo><distrib><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>US Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg></cntorgp><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing</addrtype><address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address><city>Denver</city><state>CO</state><postal>80225</postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>1-888-275-8747 (1-888-ASK-USGS)</cntvoice><cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib><distliab>Although this data set has been used by the U.S. Geological
Survey, U.S. Department of the Interior, no warranty expressed or
implied is made by the U.S. Geological Survey as to the accuracy
of the data and related materials. The act of distribution shall not 
constitute any such warranty, and no responsibility is assumed by 
the U.S. Geological Survey in the use of this data, software, or 
related materials.
Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive 
purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. 
Government.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>Tabular Digital Data Set</formname></digtinfo><digtopt><onlinopt><computer><networka><networkr>https://doi.org/10.5066/F7XW4J1J</networkr></networka></computer></onlinopt></digtopt></digform><fees>None. This dataset is provided by USGS as a public service.</fees></stdorder></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20181003</metd><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>James Falcone</cntper><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg></cntperp><cntpos>Ask USGS -- Water Webserver Team</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing</addrtype><address>12201 Sunrise Valley Dr., MS 413</address><city>Reston</city><state>VA</state><postal>20192</postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>1-888-275-8747 (1-888-ASK-USGS)</cntvoice><cntemail>https://answers.usgs.gov/</cntemail></cntinfo></metc><metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn><metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv></metainfo></metadata>